I am a recognized authority on the 4.5 tatami room.
わたしは　押しも押されもせぬ　四畳半主義者である
その空間的意義について　説明しようと思う
I think I shall expound on the aspects of that space.
Although I knew of one person who lived in a 3 tatami room,
わたしは　三畳の部屋に住んでいる人間を
１人だけ知っていたが
they grew more and more stubbornly set against the tides of the world,
断固として世に迎合しない性質が高じて
and last year their parents came from their hometown to pick them up.
昨年　郷里から親が迎えに来た
いささか　信じ難いことだが　浄土寺の近くには
It might be a little hard to believe, but near Joudo Temple
畳を２枚　縦に並べた部屋　というものが　実在するらしい
I've heard there are rooms that exist with two tatami mats laid end-to-end.
If you slept on them every night, there's no doubt you'd grow in height.
毎晩　寝ていたら　身長が伸びてしまうに違いない
In Kitashirakawa Baptist General Hospital's
XXXX ward, it's said there are 1 tatami rooms,
北白川バプテスト病院　かいわいの　…荘には
一畳の部屋があったというが
それを知った学生は　謎めいた失踪を遂げ
but the students that knew of this ended up mysteriously disappearing,
and their friends one by one all met unfortunate fates.
その知人たちも　数々の悲運に見舞われたという
And then there is the 4.5 tatami room.
そこで　四畳半である
Compared to the 1, 2, or 3 tatami rooms,
一畳や　二畳や　三畳に比べて　四畳半というものは
実に奇麗な正方形になっている
the 4.5 tatami room is a truly beautiful square.
Is it not magnificent?
美しいではないか
2 tatamis can also form a square, but it is cramped.
二畳でも正方形になるけれども　それでは手狭である
On the other hand, once you've made a square larger than 4.5 tatami,
かといって　四畳半より　広い面積で　正方形をつくると
it becomes as spacious as Takeda Shingen's lavatory, and one might even get lost.
今度は　武田　信玄の便所のように
広くて　下手をすれば遭難する
After entering university, I became a fierce supporter of the 4.5 tatami room.
大学入学以来　わたしは　この四畳半を
断固として支持してきた
Those people who live in 7, 8, or even 10 tatami rooms...
七畳やら　八畳やら　十畳やらの　部屋に住む人間は
本当に　それだけの空間を　わが物として支配するに足る
人間としての器が　あるのであろうか
Are they truly worthy of ruling over such a space as if it is their own?
われわれ　人類に支配可能なのは四畳半以下の空間であり
I wonder if human beings even have such capacity?
それ以上の広さを貪欲に求める　不届き者は
いずれ　部屋の隅から　恐るべき　反逆に遭うことであろう
We humanity have the ability to rule 4.5 tatami and smaller spaces.
Those reprehensible beings who greedily lust for larger area
そう　わたしは主張してきた
will surely be met by fearsome rebellion from some corner of their room.
四畳半こそ　わたしの世界の全てである
それは　わたしの信念でもあり　そして　今は
That was my assertion.
The 4.5 tatami room is my entire world.
客観的事実でもあった
That is my conviction, but now...
責任者は　どこか？
...there is also the objective reality of the situation.
Where is the person responsible?
hitobito wa atsui kumo ni kao wo kakushiteru
人々は厚い雲で顔を隠してる
Humans hide their faces in front of thick clouds
iki ba no nai omoi wo zutto motte toideiru
行き場のない想いをずっと持って研いでいる
Getting more and more consumed by the feeling of getting nowhere
nani mo nai machi ni umorete mo sore demo ima demo
何もない街に埋もれても それでも 今でも
Even now, they're still buried in the same empty town
tsuranaru uindou ni
連なるウィンドウに
A perfect dream of dolls lined up
narabitatsu ningyou no marui yume
並び立つ人形の悪い夢
on a stretched out window
sore to mo soko ni kakurete
それとも倉庫に隠れて
Then they hide themselves away
fusaidetatte
塞いでたって
so that they can be covered up
hokori dake kabutte mitsukaranai
埃だけ被って見つからない
Wearing only their pride, they still can't find anything
dare no te ni datte furerarenai
誰の手にだって触れられない
They still aren't touched, no matter whose hands they're in
boku tachi no genzai wo kurikaesu koto darake demo
僕たちの現在を繰り返すことだらけでも
If we repeat this moment of ours properly,
sou itsuka kimi to deaou
そういつか君と出会おう
I will meet you someday
sonna hi wo omotte hibi wo ikou
そんな日を思って 日々を行こう
Until that day is here, I will keep on going
ikou
行こう
Going
Then I was a freshman university student
当時　大学１回生だった　わたしの目の前には
and before me lay open countless doors to various different campus lives.
様々なキャンパスライフへの扉が　無数に開かれていた
But I didn't join any of the circles.
しかし　わたしは　どのサークルも選ばなかった
ばら色のキャンパスライフなど　しょせん　夢　幻である
A rose-colored campus life is, after all, nothing more than an illusory dream.
I decided to train myself in the tranquil space known as the 4.5 tatami room.
わたしは　四畳半という　静謐な空間で
自らを鍛えることにした
Terayama Shuji once said this:
"Throw away books and go out into the city."
かつて　寺山　修司は言った
「書を捨てて　町へ出ろ」と
But what was he saying to do once you go out into the city?
しかし　町に出て　何をしろというのだ
For the next two years I spent most of my time in the 4.5 tatami room,
以降　２年間　わたしは　ほとんどの時間を
四畳半において過ごし
and some people came to call me the "4.5 Tatami Ideologue."
一部で　四畳半主義者と　呼ばれるまでになっていた
"The 4.5 Tatami Ideologue"
This is my inner sanctum.
ここが　わたしの牙城である
The Eizan train runs behind it, and though it only takes a few seconds to circle this space,
裏を叡山電車が走る　１周　わずか数秒の空間ではあるが
ここには　わたしの　全てが詰まっている
everything about me is crammed in here.
To the north is a cheap, flimsy door.
北側には　薄っぺらなドアがあり
先代から由緒正しい注意書きが　健在である
A note with venerable hints from the previous occupant is still affixed there.
On one side of the door is a sink of bottomless filth,
ドアの脇には　汚れ放題の流し台があり
料理人のやる気を損なうこと　請け合いである
assuring the loss of any would-be cook's motivation.
I steadfastly refuse to try my hand at cooking,
わたしは　料理の腕を　振るうことを　断固　拒否し
「男子　厨房に入らず」を　実践してきた
putting into practice my belief that
"men shouldn't set foot in the kitchen."
The majority of the north wall is a closet,
北側の壁の大半は　押し入れとなっており
filled carelessly with unremarkable clothing and books I never read.
華やかさの　かけらもない衣類　読まなかった本などが
無造作に詰め込まれている
My library of obscenity is also within.
わいせつ図書館も　その中だ
In one corner of the east wall are a vacuum cleaner and rice cooker
東の壁の隅には　強いて使う必要性を感じない
掃除機と炊飯器が置いてあり
that do not look as if they've been heavily used,
and most of the wall is a grand library,
壁の大半には　膨大な蔵書を取り揃えた
広大な活字スペースが広がる
in which an enormous number of printed works have been assembled.
In the space between the southeast bookcase and my desk
南東の本棚と机のはざまには
あらゆる　がらくたが投げ込まれる空間が広がっており
lies an area in which various junk has been thrown,
and I believe if one were to venture into it alone and get lost,
the chances of returning alive would be slim.
そこへ　ひとたび迷い込んだが最後
生きて帰れる可能性は　極めて低いと思われた
And then from the south to the southwest
そして　南から南西へかけて　叡山電車が通ると
がたがたと震える窓があり
there is a window which rattles as the Eizan train passes by,
その手前に　高校時代から　苦楽を共にしてきた　机が置いてある
and there underneath it is placed my desk that has been with me through high school.
In the west are socks in search of lost partners,
西側には　やもめの靴下が　相手を探しており
日々の生活を彩る衣装
the clothes that make up my everyday life,
and an old-fashioned world map.
古風な世界地図がある
うわっ！　あっ　うっ…
A famous short story begins with a normal man that one morning turns into an insect.
平凡な男が　ある朝　毒虫になっていたというのは
有名な小説の冒頭である
For me it was not something so dramatic.
わたしの場合　そこまで劇的ではなかったが
これは　困ったことになった
But it had definitely become a problem.
"A proper man shall not be perturbed no matter what circumstances he might find himself in.
He must think through the situation calmly."
But as I had not had much enthusiasm for going outside previously,
しかし　これまで　熱心に　外へ出ようとしなかった者を
いまさら　慌てて　出ようとするのは
wouldn't going crazy trying to get out make me quite shallow as a human?
いかにも　人間の底が浅いではないか
腰を据えて　どっしり構えているうちに
事態は　おのずから好転するであろう
While I sat down and calmly waited it out,
the situation might well change for the better on its own.
I had come up with a single hypothesis.
わたしは　１つの仮説を立てた
It supposed that this was a curse of that old fortune teller.
占い婆の呪い仮説である
There was an old woman who emitted freely an eerie aura as I passed by Kiyamachi.
先日　木屋町を通り掛かると
怪しい妖気を　無料で　垂れ流している老婆がいた
The old woman said "Student there, you'll be in trouble soon!"
老婆は　「学生さん　そろそろ　お困りであろう」
「人生を踏み誤ってしまった」と　問うてくる
"You have made a false step in life!"
I replied "That is not the case at all! I am satisfied with the way I live!"
わたしは　「断じて　そのようなことは　ありません」
「今の暮らしで充足している」と　答えるが
But the old woman continued, "You shouldn't be so stubborn."
老婆は　続けて「意地を張らなくても　いいのですよ」と言う
「あなたは　才能がおありでしょうから
好機は　目の前に　ぶら下がっております」と
"I can sense you have talent, so there is opportunity dangling before your eyes."
That is not an opportunity or anything!
こんなもの　好機でも何でもない！
Finally the old woman went "Heh, heh, heh, heh, heh..."
最後に老婆は…　ヒヒヒヒ…　とは
言わなかったかも　しれないが　気色悪く笑っていた
Or maybe not, but she smiled evilly like that.
Hey, is anybody there?
おーい！　誰か聞こえるか！
As I cried out a line straight out of some crappy drama to no response,
三文ドラマのような　せりふを　吐いたものの　返事はなく
I had no choice but to take all the embarrassment upon myself.
その恥ずかしさを　１人で　受け止めねばならなかった
こうなると　いよいよ　ＳＦである
Well, it seems we've finally entered the realm of science fiction.
I have a feeling there was once a movie
こんなふうに　部屋がつながった世界に
閉じ込められる映画も　かつて　あった気がする
where someone was trapped in rooms connected in this way.
Since water flows out, that means it should be connected to the outside world in some way.
水が出てくるということは
外界へと　つながっているはずである
If I were some kind of mole-man and could pass through the faucet,
わたしが　蛇口を通り抜けられる軟体人間であれば
I could struggle through to Kyoto Water Bureau, but...
ここから　難なく　京都の水道局へ出られるのだが
After two or so days, I ran out of food.
約２日目にして　食料がなくなった
"A source of protein?"
"Protein?"
I was like a Robinson Crusoe washed up on a deserted 4.5 tatami room.
まるで　無人の四畳半に　流れ着いた　ロビンソン·クルーソーだが
But for me there was a faucet with water, and furniture...
わたしの場合　蛇口から水は出るし家具一式も揃っており
I had a set of everything; I could hardly call this a state of survival.
サバイバルと呼ぶにも　どうも煮えきらなかった
I had a stroke of good luck.
僥倖であった
In the 4.5 room next door there were fish burgers and a Castella.
隣の四畳半にも　魚肉ハンバーグと　カステラがあった
So then, is it okay for me to eat this?
とはいえ　これは　食べてもいいものだろうか
I don't really read much science fiction,
わたしは　ＳＦは　あまり読まないが
これが　もし　そういった現象だとしたら
so if this really is that sort of phenomenon,
would eating this Castella cause some sort of harm?
このカステラを食べることで　何か不都合は起きないのだろうか
And if this is all some sort of hallucination, is this Castella even real?
あるいは　この全てが幻覚だとしたら
このカステラは　本当に実在するものだろうか
It is a Castella.
カステラだ
Putting aside rational explanation, this was indeed an honest to goodness Castella.
合理的な説明は　ともかく
まさしく　それは　カステラであった
And so the problem of my food supply was basically solved.
こうして　食糧問題は　根本的に解決した
As I could not see the light of the sun,
太陽の光が見られぬから
昼なのか　夜なのかも　判然としない
I could not determine whether it was noon or night,
１日１日と区切っていても
and though I made it a point to delineate each day from the next,
それが正確な区切りなのかどうか　定かではなかった
I could not be sure that my delineations were correct.
I can't ignore the nutrients that I get from the Castella.
カステラによって得られる　栄養分は　無視できない
これは　先日　２階の住人の部屋に出入りする
小津という人間から　もらったものである
I got it a few days ago from a person named Ozu,
who came to visit a person who lives on the second floor.
A couple of days before I became trapped,
閉じ込められる数日前
わが　下鴨幽水荘に　ゴキブリが大量発生した
I discovered a large cockroach outbreak in our Shimogamo Yuusuisou.
"I stopped by and went to the room on the second floor. I made a cockroach cube weapon but it malfunctioned. Sorry for the inconvenience. Please, eat this. - Ozu"
At the time I felt an irrational anger come over me.
そのときは　理不尽な怒りに駆られたが
But should I not be thankful to this Ozu person now that I am in this circumstance?
今となっては　会ったことのない
小津という人間に　感謝すべきであろう
There were times I despaired, but after I thought about it,
絶望的ではあったが
考えようによっては　この状況は　幸運といえた
perhaps this situation could be called a stroke of luck?
If I transfer to the room next door I can get another Castella and more fish burgers.
隣の部屋に移れば　またカステラと魚肉ハンバーグが手に入る
I might be getting lopsided nutrition,
栄養に偏りはあるが
これで　この先　ずっと　食うには困らないというわけだ
but food would not be a problem in the foreseeable future.
With things as they are,
こうなってくると　この四畳半世界が
むしろ　住みよい世界に思えてくる
I could think of this world of 4.5 tatami rooms as a wonderful place to live.
From a physical perspective a 4.5 tatami space is quite small,
四畳半は　一見　物理的に狭いようであるが
その拡張を　インナーワールドに　求めることができる
but one can find an expansive inner world from within.
妄想世界を広げるのに　制限はない
Within the world of imagination there are no boundaries.
It could be said that I am the ultimate creator of this 4.5 tatami room!
いうなれば　ここ　四畳半において
わたしは　万物の創造主たり得るのだ
I will survive.
生きぬいてやろう
I will have fun persisting in this perfect 4.5 tatami world!
この　四畳半というパーフェクトワールドを楽しみぬいてみせよう
That way I will show this god of fate who is boss!
それが　運命の神への　仕返しであるように思え
わたしは　武者震いをした
I trembled with excitement!
"This is coffee."
I thought that I might take this opportunity to read the books I had not read.
これを機に　読めていなかった本を
読んでしまおうと思う
時間は　いくらでもある
I have as much time as I need!
This is fun! This is fun! This is fun!
楽しい　楽しい　うっ　楽しい…
Sometimes to pass the time I would admirably think to study,
たまに　暇に任せて
勉強でもしようと　殊勝な考えを　起こし
but Schrödinger's equation knocked me out.
シュレーディンガー方程式に　返り討ちにされたりした
As a pioneer in this 4.5 tatami world, I wove a plan to bravely make my life here.
この四畳半世界の　開拓者として
１人　雄々しく　生き延びていく計画を練った
I would devise ways to use the Castella and fish burgers to make various other dishes.
カステラと　魚肉ハンバーグを使って
もっと　多様な料理を工夫し
キノコの計画的　栽培事業にも着手
I would undertake operation of a systematic system of growing mushrooms!
I would even remodel many of the rooms into a bowling alley,
いずれは　各部屋を改装して
ボウリング場や　映画館　ゲームセンターなどの
各種　アミューズメント施設を造り
or movie theater, or arcade, and create all kinds of different amusement centers!
理想郷を　実現しよう
I would realize my own Utopia!
Just thinking about it made me excited!
考えるだけで　わくわくする
Even doing something as shameful as this, no one in the world would pay any heed.
こんな　まぬけなことを　していても
世界中の誰も　わたしのことを　気に掛けない
他人に　煩わされることのない
I will not be pestered by other people.
まさに　わたしだけの世界
It is indeed a world just for myself.
Absorbing myself in reading 20,000 Leagues Under the Sea,
『海底二万海里』を　読みふけり
I got drunk on cheap whiskey and cried out toward the ceiling.
安い　ウイスキーで酔っぱらい
天井に向かって　わめき続ける
Becoming afraid of the silent world pressing down around me,
己を押し包む　無音の世界が　怖くなり
I sang all the songs I knew at the top of my lungs.
知っているかぎりの歌を　大声で歌うに　至り
わたしは　この四畳半世界から
脱出したくなっている自分を　発見した
And so I discovered that I myself wanted to escape from this 4.5 tatami world.
I didn't want to admit, but I was completely and utterly sick of this 4.5 tatami room.
認めたくないことではあったが
わたしは　四畳半に　心底　うんざりしていた
ドアを開ければ　汚い廊下があり
If I opened the door to the dirty hallway and headed down that dirty hallway,
汚い廊下を抜けていけば　汚い便所があって　汚い靴箱があり
there would be the dirty bathroom, and the dirty shoe boxes,
and then I could exit the boarding house to the outside.
この下宿から　外へ出ることができる
It was because I could always go outside when I pleased
いつでも　その気になれば　外へ出ることができるからこそ
that I confined myself to the 4.5 tatami room.
四畳半に　籠城できたのである
The most real thing to me was a single physiological need I was struggling with.
何より　現実的には　もう一つの　生理的欲求が
わたしを　じわじわと苦しめた
To put it plainly, I couldn't stand the smell.
平たく言えば　臭くて　たまらなくなった
One day I couldn't stand it anymore,
ある日　とうとう　耐えられなくなり
"Lavatory"
わたしは　その部屋から遠ざかり
and I hastily left on a journey to get far away from that room.
勢い　そのまま　旅に出ることにした
It must have been a week since I'd been trapped in this mysterious world.
この謎めいた世界に　閉じ込められて
およそ　１週間目のことである
とにかく　この四畳半の道を　行けるところまで　行ってみよう
Anyway, let's see how far these 4.5 tatami rooms go...
That day I must have traversed over 100 4.5 tatami rooms,
その日は　１００余りの四畳半を　横切ったが
それでも　四畳半は続き
and yet they still continued.
さすがに　アホらしくなってきた
Eventually I felt like a fool.
"Alchemy"
When I went searching in the space between my desk
シベリア流刑地といわれる
机と本棚のすき間を　調査していた際
and bookshelf known as the "Siberian Penal Colony,"
貧相な財布を　発見した
I found a thin little wallet.
If each 4.5 tatami room has 1,000 yen,
それぞれの四畳半に　千円　あるとすると
１部屋　動くごとに　千円　もうかることになる
each time I move to another room I get another 1,000 yen.
If I move to 10 rooms, or 100 rooms, or 1,000 rooms...
１０部屋　動けば　１００部屋　動けば
１，０００部屋　動けば…
I made a curious discovery.
奇妙なことを　発見した　休憩がてら　以前
While taking a break I thought to read
The Curious Casebook of Inspector Hanshichi,
古本市で買った　『半七捕物帳』を　読もうと思ったら
その四畳半には　『半七捕物帳』が　存在しなかった
which I had bought at a used book fair,
but it didn't exist in that 4.5 tatami room.
The collections on each bookshelf were different, if only slightly.
かすかな変化だが
本棚の　品揃えが　変わっていたのだ
I noticed that although at a glance the 4.5 tatami rooms seemed identical,
どうやら　詳細に見ていくと
まったく同じに見える四畳半にも
少しずつ　違いがあるらしいと　気付いた
they were each slightly different.
Oh, it was all a dream!
何だ　夢だったのかあ
I wonder why I hadn't thought to break through the wall?
なぜ　壁を破ろうと　しなかったのだろう
何しろ　この壁は　隣の部屋の会話に
相づちを　打ちたくなるほど　薄いのである
After all, the walls are thin enough to be able to hear the conversations next door.
The Chinese exchange student next door would often bring his girlfriend,
隣人の　中国から来た留学生はよく
ガールフレンドを引っ張りこんで　むつ言を　交わしていた
and they'd whisper sweet nothings to each other.
I regretted from the bottom of my heart
わたしは　第二外国語として　中国語を学ばなかったことを
腹の底から後悔したものだ
that I had not studied Chinese as my second foreign language.
彼なら　わたしが　壁を打ち破り　乱入してきたとしても
Even if I broke through the wall and invaded,
I'm sure he could just laugh it off with the deep tolerance of one from the mainland.
大陸出身の懐の深さで　笑って　済ませてくれることであろう
Here we go!
よっしゃー！
"Day xxx"
Could it be that I was dead?
ひょっとすると　わたしは　死んだのではないか？
Had I fallen into a so-called 4.5 tatami hell,
四畳半地獄というようなものに　落ちて
永遠に続く苦行を　それと知らず　強いられているのではないか
forced to suffer for all eternity?
It's hard to believe... The leaves are probably turning by now on the outside.
信じ難い　外はもう　紅葉が　始まっているかもしれぬ
１，２００時間もの間　わたしは　外食をしていない
I had not eaten out for more than 1200 hours,
nor bathed in the sun's rays, nor breathed fresh air,
日光を浴びていない
新鮮な空気を吸っていない
人間と言葉を交わしていない
nor spoken with another human being!
In this room was something I did not remember.
その部屋には　見覚えのない物があった
"Lucky Cat Chinese Restaurant"
It seemed to be the signboard for some organization.
どうやら　どこかの団体の　看板のようである
このように　四畳半ごとに　違いがあるのは　なぜか
Why did the 4.5 tatami rooms have these differences?
全て同じ　わたしの　四畳半のはずなのに
They should all be my same 4.5 tatami room, so what gave rise to these small differences?
なぜ　こまごまとした違いが　生じるのか？
In the instant I grasped the structure of this 4.5 tatami world.
その瞬間　わたしは　この　四畳半世界の仕組みを　把握した
The bookshelves with books I had missed a chance to buy,
かつて　買いそびれた本が　並ぶ本棚
わたしが　入っていないはずの　サークル
circles which I shouldn't have been a member of...
I see! These are my parallel worlds!
そうなのだ　ここは　わたしの　パラレルワールドなのだ
In these how many tens of days,
この何十日もの間　わたしは
これまでの　様々な選択の中であり得た
別の平行宇宙の四畳半を　横切ってきたのだ
I had been crossing through parallel universes of 4.5 tatami rooms
for each of the various choices I could have made!
This is the dental hygienist Hanuki-san.
これは　歯科衛生士の　羽貫さんである
The previous autumn I'd heard rumors of a beautiful dental hygienist
昨年の秋に　美人歯科衛生士が
ねっとりと歯茎マッサージを　してくれるとの噂を聞き付け
that gave the most excellent gum massages,
わたしは　近所の歯科医を訪れた
and so I'd visited the local dentist.
Lately I've seen a drunk Hanuki-san looking completely different
最近　御蔭橋で酔っぱらって　欄干から叫ぶ
まったく違う姿の羽貫さんを　見掛けたが
yelling over the railing of the Mikage bridge.
あの凛として　プロフェッショナルな
態度であった彼女に　何があったのか
I wonder what happened to that cool professional demeanor of hers?
But a mental ruffian such as myself was not able to grasp the subtlety of it.
わたしのような　精神的無頼漢には
そうした機微を　のみ込みようもなかった
どういった選択をしたのか
I wonder what choice I made?
この世界で
In this world I was close to Hanuki-san,
わたしは　羽貫さんと　親しくなり
美しいラブドールと　同棲し
I lived together with a beautiful love-doll,
and I even seemed to have exchanged letters with a proper lady.
清楚な　乙女との文通まで　果たしているらしい
実に　あやかりたい所業である
It was a situation I could only dream of.
This one looked like a lifestyle that had fallen into depravity.
どうやら　ことさら
自堕落な　生活に陥ってしまった　パターンである
Almost like I had become the disciple
まるで　わが下鴨幽水荘の　２階の住人に
弟子入りでもしたかのようだ
of that person on the second floor of the Shimogamo Yuusuisou.
I threw away my backpack filled with 1,000 yen bills.
わたしは　千円の詰まった　リュックサックを
打ち捨てていくことにした
It's not like I would ever make use of it.
どうせ　もう　わたしに使い道はないのだ
T-This is...
うっ　これは　代理戦争の軍資金か
Funds for continuing the Proxy war?
The occupant of this room seemed like they reached toward the heavens.
この部屋の住人は　やけに　上昇志向があるようだ
I remembered feeling somewhat afraid.
わたしは　やや　怒りを覚えた
Did I search for an even greater happiness than this?
これ以上の幸せを　望むというのか
Isn't that almost like Icarus flying toward the sun?
それでは　まるで　太陽を目指した　イカロスではないか
Come to think of it, I recall seeing a flier about something like this.
そういえば　そんなチラシも　かつて　見たような気がする
Isn't this that fellow I've seen at Neko Ramen?
これは　いつか　猫ラーメンで　見掛けた　人物ではないか
It's rumored that Neko Ramen uses actual cats in its broth, but the taste is unmatched.
猫ラーメンは　猫から　だしを　とっているという噂であるが
その味は　無類である
It was a calm conversation that reminded me of youth.
それは　ある青春の終わりを　思わせるような
和やかな　会談であった
I overheard the two worrying about who would succeed them in continuing some battle,
２人は　何か　争いを続けていたらしく
跡目を　誰にするかなど　不穏な話も　聞こえたが
見ると　１人は　水も滴る　いい男で
but one of them was a fine specimen of a man
while the other was a resident of Shimogamo Yuusuisou with a face like an eggplant.
もう１人は　ナスのような顔をした下鴨幽水荘の住人である
I usually thought of that man as someone I did not want to associate with.
そっちの男は　普段から　かかわりたくないと思っていた
But to think it was that ladies' man who had such a "hobby"...
しかし　あの色男に　こんな趣味があったとは
For some strange reason I began to feel attached to these people I barely knew.
何だか　よくも知らない人たちのことが
妙に　いとおしくなった
I felt as if I'd known them a long time, yet all that remained was this feeling of nostalgia.
昔から　知っていたような気がして
なぜか　懐かしささえ覚えた
Did you get paid?
「ギャラは　ちゃんともらえた？」
「カメラマンから　口説かれてない？」
Didn't the cameraman hit on you?
Not having a single person make fun of me for doing a thing like this was hard to take.
こんなことをしていても
誰一人　バカにしてさえくれない　ことが　つらかった
If there were some slippery evil companion here with me...
もし　ここに　ぬらりひょんのような
悪友の１人でもいれば
「何を　やってるんですか？」
「大脳新皮質に　うじ虫でも　湧きましたか？」
What do you think you're doing?
Are there maggots crawling around your cerebral cortex?
そう　わたしを　完膚なきまでに　バカにしてくれたことであろう
...I'm sure they would have completely belittled me like that.
And yet every occupant of every room seemed to be having fun.
それにしても　どの部屋の住人もいかにも　楽しげに見える
Even if it wasn't rose-colored,
決して　ばら色とまでは　いかないまでも
それぞれの四畳半が　それぞれに彩りに
あふれているように見える
I could see each 4.5 tatami room had its own color to it.
Was it possible for me to have made these choices, I wonder?
わたしにも　こんな選択が　可能であったのだろうか？
Ah, it's me!
ああ　お…　俺だ
Hey, you!
ああ！　おい　お前　助けてくれ！
Help me, please!
But I had already realized.
しかし　わたしは　すでに　気付いていた
My fate would change from even the tiniest of choices.
ほんの　ささいな決断の違いで　わたしの運命は変わる
無数のわたしが　生まれる
An innumerable number of I's are born,
無数の四畳半が　生まれる
an innumerable number of 4.5 tatami rooms are born.
In other words, theoretically this 4.5 tatami world has no end!
従って　この四畳半世界は　原理的に　果てはないのだ
Anyway, it seems like these fellows can cross through the parallel worlds and gather in them one after another.
どうやら　彼らは　平行世界を　超えて
次々と　集まってこられるらしい
They can lose their heart with love or liven it up with raunchy stories.
恋に　うつつを抜かすことも　できるし
わい談で　盛り上がることもできる
On the contrary, I only tell raunchy stories to myself,
それに　引き換え　わたしは　１人で　わい談し
１人で　妄想を膨らますばかりだ
always absorbed in my solitary delusions.
しかし　それも　今や　続かない
But that can no longer continue.
tengoku iku tame mainichi kosotto
天国　いくため　毎日こそっと
In order to go to heaven. Everyday, I quietly
naishou de ii koto shiteta kedo
内緒で　いいこと　してたけど
and privately do good deeds
namida hitohira
涙ひとひら
But a single teardrop
atama kurakura
あたまくらくら
Sends my head spinning
ano ko hasuppa koi dorobou
あの娘　はすっぱ　恋泥棒
That stupid girl, that love thief
watashi kenage ii hito
わたしけなげ　いいひと
I am a good and pure person
kanawanakatta koigokoro
叶わなかった恋心
My longing heart was not fulfilled
kamisama doushite
神様どうして
Why, god?
yurusanakucha koi dorobou
ゆるさなくっちゃ恋泥棒
I must forgive her. That love thief
ano ko tabun ii hito
あの娘たぶん　いいひと
Maybe she was actually a good person
wasurenakucha konna koto
忘れなくっちゃこんなこと
I have to forget all these things
watashi wa tengoku
わたしは天国
I'm in heaven
yurusanakucha
ゆるさなくっちゃ
I have to forgive her!